one way in which the hardware can help the
operating
system
managing the memory while checking for correctness
and
ensuring everything is done in the right way
could be through
base and limit registers
this is a very simple approach but it allows
us to start
observing how the hardware can help
we know that in memory we use some portion
of the memory
for keeping the operating system and then
we have portions
that are actually used to maintain the information
of the
process so for each process we could
define two numbers
basically two addresses the base one which
is the one at
which the memory used by a specific process
starts and the
limit which is basically what
you
need to sum to
the base to reach the final address or the
final address
it doesn't really matter
now what we can have is two registers one
in which we will
keep the base address and one in which we
keep the limit
and use these registers to check if a process
is accessing
its own memory or trying to access others'
memory
so this is an example about the process
A it has a specific range of addresses that
it can access
and one way to go here is to use the hardware
so that it does like this
when the CPU tries to access a specific address
the first
thing we check is whether the address is greater
than the
base address
if it is then we'll check whether it's less
than the base
plus the limit
if it is then we let the CPU access the memory
otherwise in any of the other two cases
we let the hardware
generate a trap generate a message an alert
so that the hardware
itself can stop once it is done with the execution
of this
instruction and when it goes to checking
what should be
the following instruction it goes and senses
they interrupt
line since there is such an interrupt wakes
up the operating
system and lets the operating system take
a decision about
what to do with this process that is trying
to access memory
that does not belong to it
now the important thing here is of course
to define these
two registers or the operations we want to
do with these registers
basically to read and write especially
to write the values
of the base and the limit register as privileged
instructions
which means that only the operating system
when is running
in kernel mode can change these addresses
we can do this during a context switch while
the user cannot
change them which means that as long as the
user or the
process that is run by a certain user tries
to access memory
that does not belong to its own process the
operating system
will wake up and do something about it kill
the process
or create an alert for the process and so
on and so fort
now we actually know that the operating system
is more powerful
than any other process because it can run
in kernel mode
and it can of course not only read the memory
of other
processes but also modify the registers that
refer to other
processes without restrictions
and we already saw an example of this and
now you probably
should understand why things are starting
to fit together
in this example in which we had the fork and
we were creating
a new process and then calling exec to replace
the memory
you can see that now when you replace the
memory of the process
with other information with information that
belongs to another
program the amount of memory that a new program
will need
is not necessarily the same
which means that you might need to change
the base or the
limit register depending on where you place
the new information
and you can imagine the operating system is
the one that
is doing this and that's why you give power
to the operating
system through the system
call fork when you create a new process
or in this case through exact when you
want to replace
the memory of the new process